<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2006-2008, The University of Manchester, UK.

This file is part of PsyGrid.

PsyGrid is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as 
published by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of 
the License, or (at your option) any later version.

PsyGrid is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public 
License along with PsyGrid.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<chapter id="dsd">
  <title>openCDMS Create</title>

  <para>openCDMS Create facilitates the design and configuration of studies
  (datasets) to be used for data collection with openCDMS Collect. This guide
  describes how to quickly set up a study and the features and settings
  available within the openCDMS Create application.</para>

  <section id="dsdwizardterminology">
    <title>Wizard Set-up</title>

    <para>A wizard feature for quick creation of studies. Use the 'Next' and
    'Back' buttons to navigate through the wizard. The 'Finish' button will
    create the new study and the 'Cancel' button will dismiss the wizard
    without creating a study.</para>

    <section id="dsdwizardpageone">
      <title>Wizard Page One - Study Identifiers and Properties</title>

      <para>The initial wizard page for configuring a study. The 'Next' button
      will not be enabled (clickable) until a Study Name nad Study Code have
      been entered.</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_wizard1.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <section id="dsdwizardstudyname">
        <title>Study name</title>

        <para>A short name for the study should be entered in this field (e.g.
        Outlook or National Eden). This is used (in conjunction with the study
        code) to uniquely identify the study. If you enter a name for the
        study that already exists in the database (i.e. a name that represents
        another study that has been saved either by you or by another user),
        an error dialog will be produced when you click 'Next' and you will
        not be allowed to proceed. New studies must have a unique name and
        study code.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdwizardstudycode">
        <title>Study code</title>

        <para>A short code for the study (e.g. OLK or NEDEN). This is used for
        study identifiers (e.g. OLK/001001-1 might identify the first
        participant in the Outlook study in the Manchester centre). The code
        is always used for display purposes in the various openCDMS
        applications. The study code is used (in conjunction with the study
        name) to uniquely identify the study. If you enter a code for the
        study that already exists in the database (i.e. a code that represents
        another study that has been saved either by you or by another user),
        an error dialog will be produced when you click 'Next' and you will
        not be allowed to proceed. New studies must have a unique name and
        study code.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdwizardstudydescription">
        <title>Study Description</title>

        <para>A short overview of the study aims (e.g. "A study to track a
        large, representative cohort of individuals with first episode
        psychosis").</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdwizardstudyscope">
        <title>Study scope</title>

        <para>Describes the geographical scope of the study - either a single
        centre study or a multi-centre study. Note: this option is not
        available to studies without preconfigured centres.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdwizardstudycentre">
        <title>Study centre</title>

        <para>Set the name of the single-centre for the study here. Note: the
        option is not available to studies without preconfigured
        centres.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdwizarduserandomisation">
        <title>Use randomisation</title>

        <para>An on/off flag for setting whether the study is to be randomised
        or not. If selected, randomisation settings must be completed before
        the study can be successfully saved to the database. For more
        information on randomisation settings, see the section on
        Randomization below.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdwizardstudystages">
      <title>Wizard Page - Study Stages</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_wizard2.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>This is the second page of the study wizard and requires entries
      to define the time stages in the study for which documents must be
      completed (e.g. Screening, Baseline, Day 1, Day 7 etc.) Clicking the
      'Add' button produces a dialog that requires a name for the new Study
      Stage (e.g. 'Screening'). When 'ok' is clicked in this dialog, the study
      stage is added to the study and is displayed in the list of configured
      Study Stages in the list.</para>

      <section id="dsdwizardreorderstudystages">
        <title>Reorder Study Stages</title>

        <para>Select a study stage in the list and then use the up and down
        arrow keys to change the order of study stages for the study. This is
        a useful option if an error is made in the original addition of
        studies (e.g. 'Day 7' is added before 'Day 2').</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdwizardstudyprocedures">
      <title>Documents</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_wizard3.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>A list of all possible documents that must be completed for the
      study (e.g. Medical History, Vital Signs). A document represents a form
      or assessment that must be completed for the study.</para>

      <section id="dsdwizardreorderstudyprocedures">
        <title>Reorder documents</title>

        <para>Select a document in the list and then use the up and down arrow
        keys to change the order of documents for the study. The reordering
        functions similarly to the reordering of study stages described
        above.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdwizardvisitschedule">
      <title>StudySchedule</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_wizard4.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>This wizard page that displays a grid for describing which
      documents should be completed at which stages in the study. Click on a
      square in the grid to select or deselect. It is possible to assign a
      document to more than one than one stage. Each document must be assigned
      to at least one stage.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdmenus">
    <title>Menus</title>

    <para>This section provides a description of top level menu options
    availabe in openCDMS Create.</para>

    <section id="dsdfilemenu">
      <title>File Menu</title>

      <para>This menu contains the major operations for opening, closing
      saving and creating a new studies and documents.</para>

      <section>
        <title>New Study Wizard</title>

        <para>This option launches the new study wizard (as described in the
        previous section).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Open</title>

        <para>The allows a study to be opened either from a file location
        (local or network) or from the openCDMS database. Selecting this
        option opens a new window from which the destination of the file or
        saved study can be chosen. Options exists within this window to choose
        from either the Database or from the File System. Files can be
        selected for opening either by double-clicking on them in the window
        or clicking once and then selecting the 'Open' button. Similarly in
        the database view, studies can be opened by double-clicking on them or
        by clicking once and then selecting the 'Open' button.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Open Library View</title>

        <para>This launches the Library view. For more details on how to use
        the Library, please see the next chapter.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Close</title>

        <para>This removes the current study from the active view. If the
        study has been edited since it was last saved, close will produce a
        dialog prompting to save changes.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Save (to File or to Database)</title>

        <para>This saves the currently open study to either a file location or
        to the database (depending on the location from which the file was
        last saved or opened from). The parenthetical comment indicates the
        destination to which the study will be saved. Details of the success
        or failure of this operation will be viewable in the status
        bar.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Save As</title>

        <para>This allows the currently open study to be saved to either a
        file location or to the database. Selecting this menu item produces a
        new window where the desired saved destination can be chosen.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Publish</title>

        <para>This publishes the study to the database. Publishing a study to
        the database is the final step in the study design process and it
        should only be done after the study has been validated (using the
        Preview option). After publishing a study, it will no longer be
        possible to save the study to the database. Effectively, publishing
        locks the study in the database and indicates that it is now ready for
        data collection process to commence. If you wish to store a copy of
        the study to the database but you do not want this to be final version
        to be released then you should use the 'Save' menu item described
        above.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Patch Live Study</title>

        <para>This menu item patches a live, published study to the database
        and should be used with caution. Patching changes cannot be undone.
        This is the option to use to update a live study (e.g. to add a new
        document to the study).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Preview</title>

        <para>Preview launches the currently open study in openCDMS Collect.
        This allows you try out your study design and verify that you have
        configured everything correctly before saving it to the database. It
        is recommended that studies are regularly previewed in Collect to
        ensure that they conform to the study requirements.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Properties</title>

        <para>This displays the basic properties for the currently open study.
        Properties such as study name, study code and study description are
        viewable and configurable from here.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Exit</title>

        <para>This causes the application to quit. You will be asked to
        confirm this step to ensure that you do not exit accidentally.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdstudymenu">
      <title>Study Menu</title>

      <para>This menu contains the major operations for managing attributes
      associated with study design. It contains the options to create and edit
      units, validation rules, transformers, study stages, consent, centres,
      statuses, reports and randomisation.</para>

      <section>
        <title>New Document</title>

        <para>This creates a new document in the currently open study. This
        menu item is only enabled when a study is already open.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Units</title>

        <para>This permits the creation and management of units to be used
        with the study. Units are managed on a per-study basis and can be
        assigned to individual entries using the individual entry
        configuration dialogs.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Transformers</title>

        <para>This permits the creation and management of transformers to be
        used with the study. Transformers are managed on a per-study basis and
        can be assigned to individual entries using the individual entry
        configuration dialogs.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Validation Rules</title>

        <para>This permits the creation and management of validation rules to
        be used with the study. Validation rules are managed on a per-study
        basis and can be assigned to individual entries using the individual
        entry configuration dialogs.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Validate Study</title>

        <para>The study should be validated before it is saved to the
        database. A validation operation will display which components have
        been successfully completed and which ones remaining before a study is
        in a fit state to save to the database.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Study Schedule</title>

        <para>This allows management of the documents and the stages to which
        they have been assigned. A dialog is produced that displays the stages
        and documents. Assignments can be edited by clicking in the table
        checkboxes.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Reorder Documents</title>

        <para>This option allows the reordering of the doucments in the open
        study. Documents can be moved up or down by selecting the item in the
        list and clicking on the arrow buttons.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Centres</title>

        <para>This allows management of the centres for the study. Centres and
        sites can be added, edited and removed using this menu option.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Statuses</title>

        <para>This allows management of the statuses for the study. Statuses
        can be added, edited and removed using this menu option.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Study Stages</title>

        <para>This allows management of the study stages. Within this option
        is also possible to reorder the study stages by selecting the stage in
        the list and using the arrow buttons to move it up and down. The
        manual configuration of study stages available in this menu item is
        typically for advanced users to manipulate the default study stage
        settings. It is not recommended that novice users change these
        settings.</para>

        <para id="dsddocgroupvalidatepanel">Study Stage Validation: The icon
        here indicates if the document groups passes validation (a green check
        indicates success; a red X indicates failure). For validation to
        succeed, both study stages and study stasuses must be sensibly
        configued. Two checks are performed. Firstly, validation ensures that
        all update statuses for document groups are a valid transition from at
        least one of the allowed record statuses for the study stage.
        Secondly, all prerequisite groups must occur before the study stage
        for which they have been configured. Hovering the mouse over the cross
        icon will present a tooltip detailing the validation failures.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Reports</title>

        <para>This allows specification of the required reports for the
        studies.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Participant Register</title>

        <para>This produces a dialog where custom fields may be added to the
        participant register. See the section on the participant register for
        more information.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manage Randomiser</title>

        <para>This produces a dialog where the randomisation settings for the
        study must be completed. See the section on randomisation for more
        information on the required settings.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdhelpmenu">
      <title>Help Menu</title>

      <para>This menu contains the options to view the contents of the help
      manual and an about dialog to display basic properties of the
      study.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Help</title>

        <para>This option displays the help manual for openCDMS Create.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>About</title>

        <para>About shows the basic version numbers and details about openCDMS
        Create.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdoverview">
    <title>Main Design Window Overview</title>

    <para>The OpenCDMS Create application comprises three main sections that
    are viewable in the main design window.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Study Designer main window</title>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_m18108329.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <section id="dsddatasettree">
      <title>Tree Views</title>

      <para>On the leftmost pane of the main window, there are two tree views.
      When a study is opened or newly created, it appears in the tree views
      here. For names in the tree that are longer than the visible area, a
      tooltip is provided. A scrollbar is provided when study documents or
      entries extend beyond the visible portion of the tree. It is also
      possible to expand or contract the tree display area horizontally by
      clicking on the dividing scrollbar and dragging it to the left or
      right.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Design View</title>

        <para>The first view is the Design View. This is the most commonly
        used view and it shows all the documents and entries for the study.
        Double-clicking on a document or entry will open it in the document
        panel. Right-clicking on the study will provide functionality to
        create a new document in the study and to display the basic properties
        of the study. (For right-click operations relevant to the Library, see
        the section on the Library below.)</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Schedule View</title>

        <para>The second view is the Schedule View. This view shows how
        documents have been configured for particular stages in the study.
        There are no double-click operations supported in this view. To change
        the allocation of documents to study stages, you should use the Manage
        Study Schedule option in the Study Menu. It is not possible to
        manipulate documents and entries from this view; use the design view
        for viewing and editing individual documents and entries.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsddocpanel">
      <title>The Document Panel</title>

      <para>The document panel is the central component of the main openCDMS
      Create window. Documents can be viewed and edited in this view. Multiple
      documents may be opened (by double-clicking on them in the study tree)
      and will be displayed in the document panel in unique tabs. Entries can
      be dragged from the Entry Panel (on the right hand side of the screen)
      and dropped into the Document Panel to add new entries to the document.
      Right-click within the document panel on entries provided functionality
      such as the ability to copy and paste entries, to edit the entries and
      reorder the entries within the document (by moving them up and down).
      When a document is opened, it is rendered similarly to how it will
      appear in the openCDMS Collect application with a sections view on the
      top of the panel and the entries displayed below.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdentrypanel">
      <title>The Entry Panel</title>

      <para>The Entry Panel is the rightmost component of the main openCDMS
      Create window. Entries are displayed as icons - for new users, hovering
      the mouse over individual entries will provide a tooltip detailing the
      type of entry the icons represent. Entries can be added to documents to
      dragging the icon into the document to the position required. When an
      entry is added to a document, the configuration dialog for that entry
      will be opened automatically.</para>

      <section id="dsdecrfpagedescription">
        <title>Text</title>

        <para>Use this entry type to create a non-editable textual
        description. This is a useful entry to use if you wish to provide a
        short description of the section or document. Drag the icon onto the
        main document panel to add it.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdtextentry">
        <title>Text Entry</title>

        <para>Use this entry to create a question with a text-based response.
        You will prompted to choose between a single-line text entry (for
        questions requiring a short response) or a multi-line text entry (for
        questions requiring a longer response). Drag the icon onto the main
        document panel to add it.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdoptionentry">
        <title>Option Entry</title>

        <para>Use this entry to create a question with multiple pre-defined
        responses. This is the appropriate entry type to use if you wish to
        give users the ability to select the appropriate answer from multiple
        options and can be presented either in as a drop-down box or as a
        list. Drag the icon onto the main document panel to add it.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdnumericentry">
        <title>Numeric Entry</title>

        <para>Use this entry to create a question that requires a numeric
        response. You will be prompted to choose between an integer entry and
        a basic numeric entry. An integer entry is an entry that requires a
        positive or negative whole number to be input by the user (i.e
        automatic validation will take place to ensure the input number is a
        positive or negative whole number). A basic numeric entry places no
        restriction on the numeric value entered (although you can restrict
        user input using a validation rule; see the section on validation
        rules below). Drag the icon onto the main document panel to add
        it.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddateentry">
        <title>Date Entry</title>

        <para>Use this entry to create a question the requires a date response
        (e.g. Date of birth). Using this option will provide the user with the
        option to enter a date either by typing in a date in the required
        format or by selecting the date from a drop-down calendar panel. Drag
        the icon onto the main document panel to add it.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdbooleanentry">
        <title>Check Boxes</title>

        <para>Use this type of entry to create a question that requires a
        simple yes or no response. Using this option will provide the user
        with the a single check box that can be selected or deselected.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdtableentry">
        <title>Table Entry</title>

        <para>Use this entry to create a question that requires responses in
        tabular format. The table entry combines a number of basic entry types
        detailed above and presents these as one table. Entry choices
        available include a text entry, number entry, option entry and date
        entry. These entries must be added to the table in the order with
        which they are to appear in the table (i.e. from left to right).
        Additionally, is possible to add a Fixed Label Entry. The Fixed Label
        Entry is a special type of entry only for use with the table entry and
        it is used to provide row labels for the table. if the Fixed Label
        entry is used, it will not be possible for the user to add additional
        rows to the table but instead they will be required to complete each
        of the the entries for each label. The Fixed Label will always assume
        the rightmost position in the table because it is used as a row
        label.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdderivedentry">
        <title>Calculated Entry</title>

        <para>Use this entry to automatically calculate a values based on
        responses to preceding questions. You will be asked to choose between
        a calculated entry and an 'external calculated entry'. Calculated
        entries are useful for performing predefined calculations on specific
        entries (e.g. for summing up the responses to the previous entries in
        the sections). An 'external calculated entry' requires that you have a
        web service in place to perform specific calculations. Drag the icon
        onto the main document panel to add it.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dsddocconfiguration">
    <title>Configuration of Documents</title>

    <section id="dsddocconfigprops">
      <title>Document Properties</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_docconfig.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <section id="dsddocconfigname">
        <title>Name</title>

        <para>Enter a name for the document. This should be a short name for
        the document that is displayed to the user in openCDMS Collect.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddocconfigdescription">
        <title>Description</title>

        <para>Enter a description for the document. This is an optional field
        used to give extra information to the user in openCDMS Collect.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddocumentconfigpermissions">
        <title>Document Permissions</title>

        <para>This is displays the permissions given to the document. It shows
        who can see or edit the document. Click on the 'view/edit' button for
        more detailed information.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddocumentconfigstages">
        <title>Select stages for the Document</title>

        <para>This is displays the study stages that the document will appear
        in.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dsddocsections">
    <title>Document Sections</title>

    <para>Sections are used to divide an document into logical segments.
    Sections are used for display and navigation purposes. By default, a 'Main
    Section' is created. To create new sections or edit existing ones,
    right-click on the 'Manage Sections' button in the main document
    view.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Section Edit Dialog</title>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_sectioneditdialog.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>Again the name and display text fields must be completed. The
    section description section is optional. <emphasis role="bold">Note: The
    'Multiple Sections Allowed' field should only be checked if the document
    requires that dynamic sections can be added. Usually, this field will be
    left unchecked</emphasis>. When you are satisfied with your entries, click
    'OK'.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdentryconfiguration">
    <title>Configuration of Entries</title>

    <section id="dsdentryconfigbasicprops">
      <title>Basic Entries Properties</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_textentry.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigname">
        <title>Name</title>

        <para>Enter a name for the entry. This should be a short name for the
        entry that can be used to reference it within other configuration
        options (e.g. option dependencies, values for derived entries etc.)
        The primary function of the 'name' field is for configuring the study
        and it will not be displayed to the user in openCDMS Collect.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigdisplaytext">
        <title>Display Text</title>

        <para>Enter a name for the entry. This is the name of the entry that
        will be displayed to the user.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfignumber">
        <title>Number</title>

        <para>This is the label that will appear to the user before the entry
        name. Typically, numbered labels such as 1, 2, 3, might be entered
        here to identify the entries in the document sequentially.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigentrystatus">
        <title>Entry Status</title>

        <para>This field determines which status the entry will be in -
        MANDATORY: the field must be completed by the user; OPTIONAL: the
        field may or not be completed by the user; DISABLED: the field will be
        ineditable (greyed out) to the user (typically this is used when the
        entry is controlled by option dependencies.)</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigpermissions">
        <title>Entry Permissions</title>

        <para>This displays the permissions given to the entry. It shows who
        can see or edit the response to the entry. Click on the 'view/edit'
        button for more detailed information about the current entry.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfighelptext">
        <title>Help Text</title>

        <para>This field allows a text entry for providing information to the
        user about how to respond to this entry.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigstandardcodes">
        <title>Disable Missing Codes</title>

        <para>This checkbox determines whether the missing codes will be
        displayed for this entry or not (missing codes include for example
        'Not Applicable' and 'Data unable to be captured'). This box should be
        checked if you want the user to be forced to enter a value for the
        question or to choose from a predefined list of configured
        options.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigfontstyle" label="" lang="" os="">
        <title>Font Style</title>

        <para>Select the font style of the displayed text. (Header: large,
        bold text.) This is particularly useful for displaying headers within
        a document.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigshowoptioncodes">
        <title>Show Option Codes</title>

        <para>For an option, selecting this checkbox will make the option
        codes visible (option codes are configurable during the creation of
        options.) Option codes are typically numbered labels for the
        individual options.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigshowoptiondropdown">
        <title>Use drop-down selection box</title>

        <para>Display the options as a drop-down box rather than as a
        selectable list of radio buttons.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdentryconfigelementpatchingaction">
        <title>Element Patching Action</title>

        <para>If this is a published study and a new entry has been added,
        this option must be configured. A drop-down selection box is presented
        to allow users to choose between the "Reject existing elements" and
        "Accept existing documents". These options describes the action that
        will be taken to udpate existing documents that are already part of
        existing records (i.e. those documents that have been completed by
        users of openCMDS Collect). Setting the action here to be "Reject
        existing documents" will cause all existing documents to be
        automatically set to the rejected state and will therefore require
        that the user fills out the new entry manually. Selecting "Accept
        existing documents" will enter a default missing code "Not Applicable"
        and will therefore not require manual changes by the user. By defaut,
        this option is selected.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsdoptiondependencies">
        <title>Option Dependencies</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Option Dependencies</emphasis>For some
            entries, you may wish to define a dependency between this entry
            and another entry. For example, a question on pregnancy may be
            enabled/disabled by the participant's gender. To create this kind
            of dependency. First create the entry on which the question
            depends. In this case we create the gender question. To create an
            option entry, we complete the basic entry properties as before.
            Additionally we create options for the entry as follows:</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Configure Option Entry dialog</title>

              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo></screeninfo>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_af0be6a.jpg" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </figure>

            <para>Click the "Add" button to create a new option and fill in
            the required fields. Repeat this process for all required options.
            In this case, we just create 'Male' and 'Female'.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Add Option dialog</title>

              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo></screeninfo>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_21a82136.jpg" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </figure>

            <para>Next we create the pregnancy option entry. In the same way
            as before we create the options 'Yes' and 'No'. This time, however
            we set the Entry Status of the option entry to 'DISABLED'. This
            means the option entry will initially be greyed out and will not
            require the user to enter a value for it. Now we click the 'Option
            Dependencies' tab and define a dependency.</para>

            <para>Here, we assign the option 'Gender-female' and set the
            Status to 'MANDATORY'. This ensure that if the option 'Female' is
            selected by the user, the pregnancy question will be mandatory and
            must be completed.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Configure Entry - Option Dependencies</title>

              <screenshot>
                <screeninfo></screeninfo>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_1c1e0086.jpg" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdmanageunits">
      <title>Manage Units</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_confunits.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Provides the capability for adding, removing and changing the
      units for the study. To add a unit, click the 'add' button a
      configuration dialog for creating a new unit will be provided. For
      editing a unit, select the unit in the list and a configuration dialog
      will be produced. Similarly, to remove a unit, select the unit in the
      list and click 'Remove'. A description of the configuration options for
      creating and editing units is described below. The 'Ok' button will save
      the configured units. 'Cancel' will exit from the units management
      window and will not save the changes. 'Apply' will instantly save any
      changes made to the units to the study; this is a useful option if you
      wish to define base units within a single units management
      session.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdunitsabbr">Abbreviation: Provide a short abbreviation
          of the unit (e.g. "mg", "kg").</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdunitsdescription">Description: Provide a textual
          description of the units (e.g. "milligrams", 'kilograms").</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdunitsbaseunit">Base Unit: This can be used to convert
          any value having this unit to the units of the base unit by
          multiplying the value by the factor.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdunitsfactor">Factor: The factor used to convert a value
          having this unit to the units of the base unit by
          multiplication.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdmanagevalidationrules">
      <title>Manage Validation Rules</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_confvalidationrule.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Provides the capability for adding, removing and changing the
      validation rules for the study. Use the add, edit and remove buttons to
      manage validation rules. Adding, editing, removing, saving and canceling
      operations available in this dialog function like the operations
      described for units above. The 'View Tests' button is used within the
      Library mode and is described the Element Library section. A short
      overview of the general fields for validation rules is now provided
      before a more in-depth description of specific fields for particular
      kinds of validation rules.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdvalruledescription">Description: Provide a short
          description of the validation rule e.g. Number &gt; 0 and &lt;
          5.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdvalrulemessage">Message: Provide a description that
          will be displayed to the user when the rule is violated. e.g. The
          number must be greater than 0 and less than 5.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdvalruletype">Type: Select the type of validation rule
          depending on the kind of contraints you wish to apply, a numeric
          range, a date range etc.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section id="dsdvalruletextrule">
        <title>Type of Rules</title>

        <para id="dsdvalruletext">Text Validation Rule : Use this kind of rule
        to restrict a textual entry to a particular pattern and/or
        length.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruletextlowerlimit">Lower Limit: the minimum
            number of letters the response must contain</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruletextupperlimit">Upper Limit: the maximum
            number of letter the response must contain</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruletextpattern">Patterm: A regex expression to
            use for constraining the entry.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruletextpatterndetails">Pattern Details: A short
            summary description of the pattern.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para id="dsdvalruleinteger">Integer Validation Rule : Use this kind
        of rule to set acceptable ranges on an integer entry. (An integer is a
        positive or negative whole number e.g. -1, -2, 1, 2, 3).</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruleintegerlowerlimit">Lower Limit: the minimum
            integer that can be entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruleintegerupperlimit">Upper Limit: the maximum
            integer that can be entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para id="dsdvalrulenumber">Number Validation Rule : Use this kind of
        rule to set acceptable ranges on a number entry.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalrulenumberlowerlimit">Lower Limit: the minimum
            number that can be entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalrulenumberupperlimit">Upper Limit: the maximum
            number that can be entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Date Validation Rule : Use this kind of rule to constrain a date
        entry to particular values.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruledateabslowerlimit">Absolute Lower Limit: The
            minimum date that may be entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruleabsupperlimit">Absolute Upper Limit: The
            maximum date that may be entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruledaterellowerlimit">Relative Lower Limit: The
            range from today that specifies the minimum date that can be
            entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruledaterellowerlimitunits">Relative Lower Limit
            Units: The timeframe used in conjuction with the value entered in
            the 'relative lower limit'.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruledaterelupperlimit">Relative Upper Limit: The
            range from today that specifies the maximum date that can be
            entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para id="dsdvalruledaterelupperlimitunits">Relative Upper Limit
            Units: The timeframe used in conjuction with the value entered in
            the 'relative upper limit'.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdmanagetransformers">
      <title>Manage Transformers</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_transformers.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>Provides the capability for adding, removing and changing the
      transformers for the study. The operations to add, edit, remove, ok and
      cancel function as in the manage units dialog described above. The View
      Tests button is only relevant in the Element Library view as descibed in
      the Library documentation.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdtransformertype">Type of the new transformer: Choose
          from either the preconfigured transformers or define your
          own.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdtransnamespace">Web service namespace: Set the
          namespace of the web-service that the transformer utilizes to
          perform data transformation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdtransoperation">Web service operation: Set the
          operation of the web-service that the transformer utilizes to
          perform data transformation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdtransurl">Web service URL: Set the URL of the
          web-service that the transformer utilizes to perform data
          transformation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdtransresultclass">Result class: Get the name of the
          sub-class of Value that the result of the transformation will be
          stored in.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para id="dsdtransviewableoutput">Viewable Output: Set the value of
          the viewable output flag. If true, the output of the transformation
          can be viewed by humans; if false the output of the transformation
          should not be viewed by humans</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdcollabediting">
    <title>Collaborative Study Editing</title>

    <para>Since Release 6.1 of openCDMS Create, it is possible for multiple
    users to work on a single study design. Using the File-&gt;Open menu it is
    possible for individual users to access study design files on their local
    computer or a network drive. It is also possible to access studies in the
    database. Note: a user must have the correct user privileges in the study
    to load it from the database. If you want to grant access to another user
    to view and edit a study in the database, use openCDMS Control to assign
    the user access to the study. The recommended mode for collaborating on
    studies is to save intermediate designs to the database and for each user
    to load the latest version from the database each time and resave the
    changed version to the database when they are finished working on it. This
    guarantees that the database always contains the latest version of the
    study and ensures that openCDMS has full control over managing the study
    revision and update process. If you wish to collaborate using network
    files, openCDMS will make a best effort to ensure that files are managed
    correctly within the application. Due to the variation in underlying
    operation systems and networks over which openCDMS obviously does not have
    full control, it is not possible to guarantee that this functionality will
    be able to work correctly in all situations. Therefore, saving to the
    database is the recommended method for study collaboration as described
    above. In the case of accessing a network file that another user already
    has open, openCDMS will permit access in read-only mode.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdstudystages">
    <title>Study Statuses and Valid Next Statuses</title>

    <para>Study statuses and valid next statuses are automatically configured
    for studies and should only be changed by advanced users.</para>

    <para>Statuses and valid next statuses must be configured for the study. A
    study has a status that describes in high level terms how a record
    progresses during its lifetime. For instance, typical statuses might be
    "Referred", "Consented", "Complete", "Withdrawn", "Deceased", etc. All
    records in the Dataset will always reference one of the Dataset's
    statuses. As well as defining the statuses themselves, we define the
    transitions between them.</para>

    <para>A new status is created using the 'Add' button.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>New Dataset Configuration Dialog - Statuses and
      Transitions</title>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_m7e01c066.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>Each of the fields for a new status should be completed. Status name
    requires a short entry to describe the status for a record (e.g. Screened,
    Baseline Completed, Consented). The code field requires a numbered entry
    (e.g. 0, 1, 2). A generic state must also be assigned to each status: this
    generic state maps the new status onto a state recognised by openCDMS
    Collect. It might be desirable to define specific statuses for a given
    study (e.g. for more fine-grained reporting purposes) but it is necessary
    to map this new status onto a generic state so that it can be used and
    recogised by openCDMS Collect. A description of each of the Generic States
    follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>REFERRED - entered study but cannot yet be collected.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ACTIVE - in study, data being collected</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>LEFT- left/withdrawn from the study. No more data expected to be
        collected.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>COMPLETED - Completed all phases of the study and there is no
        more data to collect.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>INACTIVE - Consented into study but later withdrew all
        consent.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>INVALID - Record added by mistake or duplicated.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Add status dialog</title>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_m6234ed4.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>When two of more statuses have been defined, it is possible assign
    valid next statuses to control the flow of data entry within the
    application. For example, you may wish to allow transitions from Consent
    to Referred.</para>

    <para>To do this, ensure that status1 is selected in the drop down box as
    show above, then select status2 in the 'next valid statuses' box and click
    the -&gt; button to move the state to the valid next statuses list.
    Assigned transitions describe the possible flow of a record from one
    status to another.</para>

    <figure>
      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo />

        <mediaobject />
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdparticipantregister">
    <title>Participant Register</title>

    <para>The participant register is optionally used by studies to store the
    identifibale details of study participants e.g. name, address etc. It is
    also possible to add custom fields to the register that are specific to
    the study. This is particularly useful if non-standard parameters are
    required by the study randomizer for stratification (see <xref
    linkend="dsdrandomisationsection" />).</para>

    <para>The Manage Participant Register dialog allows custom fields to be
    added to the register. Each custom field is defined by it's name and a set
    of values which the field may take.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Manage Participant Register dialog</title>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/create_configure_register.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdrandomisationsection">
    <title>Randomization</title>

    <para>If a study is to be used for a randomised trial, it is necessary to
    configure the randomisation settings required. To configure randomisation
    settings, choose Configure Randomiser from the Study menu.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_randomiser.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <section id="dsdrandomiserstrata">
      <title>Strata</title>

      <para>To use the randomiser, it is necessary to define the parameters
      that are used to define how stratification is performed. For all studies
      sex and centre will be presented as possible stratification parameters.
      Additionally, any custom fields defined for the participant register
      (see <xref linkend="dsdparticipantregister" />) will be shown. At least
      one stratification parameter must be chosen.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdrandomisertreatments">
      <title>Treatments</title>

      <para>To use the randomiser, it is necessary to define the treatment
      arms that can be assigned. At least two treatment arms must be set. A
      name and a code for each treatment arm must be set (e.g. Treatment Name:
      Cognitive Behavioural Therapy, Treatment Code: CBT)</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdrandomiserblocksizes">
      <title>Block sizes</title>

      <para>Minimum and maximum block sizes must be set for the randomiser.
      Block sizes must be a mulitple of the number of treatments, and the
      maximum block size cannot be less than the minimum block size.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdrandomiseremails">
      <title>Randomization Emails</title>

      <para>Notification of randomisation decisions can be sent by email to
      users with the relevant roles. To set which roles receive which email
      notifications, use the check boxes.</para>

      <para>Notification of RS Decision: This will send an email when the
      treatment arm has been assigned. It will contain the participant but not
      the treatment arm.</para>

      <para>Notification of RS Invocation: This will send an email when the
      randomisation process has begun for a particular study number.</para>

      <para>Notification of RS Treatment: This will send an email containing
      the study number and the treatment arm to which the participant has been
      assigned.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdrandomisertrigger">
      <title>Randomisation Trigger</title>

      <para>In addition to the randomisation settings required here, it is
      also necessary to specifiy a document that will trigger the
      randomisation event. You must select a document from the available list.
      When the document is completed, the user will be prompted to randomise
      this participant.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdreporting">
    <title>Reporting</title>

    <para>It is possible to assign management reports at study design time. To
    configure reports, select Configure Reports from the Study menu option on
    the top menu bar. To assign reports to the study, select them from the
    left hand list and use the right arrow to associated them with the study.
    When you are finished, click OK.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_reports.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdvalidatestudy">
    <title>Validate Study</title>

    <para>To perform a basic validation check to see if the necessary
    components have been completed before saving a study, select 'Validate
    Study' from the Study Menu option on a study. Components that are
    successfully completed will display a green tick, components that are
    incomplete will show a red X. Note: studies must be fit for successful
    validation before they can be saved or published to the database. Studies
    that do not validate successfully can be saved to the file system.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dsd_validatestudy.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdconfimportmapping">
    <title>Manage Import Maping</title>

    <para>It is possible to configure a document to enable the importing of
    data from an external file source (e.g. a csv file). To configure the
    import mapping for a document, right-click on the document in the design
    view tree and select 'Manage Import Mapping'. If you wish to use the
    import mapping feature, you must select the 'Use import mapping' checkbox.
    If this is not selected, import mappings will not be aplied to the
    document. The table in this dialog contains a list of all entries in the
    document. If you wish to associate an entry with an external data source,
    you must input the appropriate column in the data source into the 'Column'
    field. Only column numbers can be entered here. Entries with a red
    background in the column field are ones that cannot be used with the
    import feature - these include text, derived entries, and composite
    entries. See the Collect user guide for information on how to import data
    into the study after you having configured the import and published your
    study. To try out the import feature before publishing your study, use the
    "Preview" feature within Create. To use the import mapping feature it is
    necessary that your import data source complies to the following
    standards: the first column must contain the identifier of the open
    participant for whom you wish to import data. No empty columns are allowed
    in your data source between this identifier column and the first column
    containing data. The first column containing data (after the identifier
    column) is column 1.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdsaving">
    <title>Autosaving</title>

    <para>Studies are autosaved every few minutes to the user's home Create
    directory with a file name of the format (Studyname-autosave.xml). Do NOT
    use this file to work with in the study designer. If you need to recover
    from an autosaved file, open the file and immediately resave it to a new
    location with a new name.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdpatching">
    <title>Patching</title>

    <para>Patching refers to the process of updating a live, published study.
    Patching live studies should be done with caution as changes made during
    patching cannot be undone. There are several possible changes that can be
    made to a study after it has been published. These will now be described
    in some detail.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchinggroups">Patching Centres and sites: It is
        possible to add additional centres and sites after the study has been
        published and then to patch these into the live study. To do this,
        open the live study and use the Menu -&gt; Manage Centres option. It
        is not possible to edit or remove existing centres and sites.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingdocuments">Patching Documents: It is possible to
        add additional documents after the study has been published and then
        to patch these into the live study. To do this, open the live study
        use the File -&gt; Open menu, and then use the 'New document' menu
        item to create new documents for the study. It is also possible to
        reorder the documents within a study using the 'Reorder Documents'
        option and also to reconfigure the study stages within which a
        document exists (see Patching: Study Stages below for more on this.
        When a document is removed from the study using the patching function,
        it will no longer be visible within openCDMS Collect or openCDMS
        Create. However, any existing data that has been entered for this
        document will be retained in the database and it will be visible in a
        data export from openCDMS Web.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingentries">Patching Documents: It is possible to
        add and edit entries to a document after the study has been published
        and then to patch these into the live study. To do this, open the live
        study use the File -&gt; Open menu, open the relevant document and
        then manipulate the entries in the usual way. Note: it is not possible
        to change the name of the entry after the study has been published.
        When an entry is removed from the study using the patching function,
        it will no longer be visible withing openCDMS Collect or openCDMS
        Create. However, any existing data that has been entered for this
        document will be retained in the database and it will be visible in a
        data export from openCDMS Web.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingstudystages">Patching Study Stages: It is
        possible to add study stages after the study has been published and
        then to patch these into the live study. To do this, open the live
        study use the File -&gt; Open menu, and then use the Manage Study
        Stages menu option from the Sutdy menu to create new study stages.
        Before patching these into the live study, it is a good idea to use
        the 'Validate Study' menu item to ensure you have configured these
        correctly. Study stages cannot be removed from the study using the
        patching function.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingstudyschedule">Patching Study Schedule: It is
        possible to modify the study schedule of a live published study. To do
        this, open the live study and use use the Manage Visit Schedule
        option. Documents removed from a particular study stage will be locked
        and no further data entry will be permissible.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingunits">Patching Units: Units may be added to the
        dataset. In addition, the assignment of units to entries can be
        changed. Use the Manage Units menu to add units to the study and use
        the Edit Entry option to modify the unit assignments of a particular
        entry.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingtransformers">Patching Transformers: Transformers
        may be added to the dataset. In addition, the assignment of
        transformers to entries can be changed. Use the Manage
        Transformersmenu to add transformers to the study and use the Edit
        Entry option to modify the transfomer assignments of a particular
        entry.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingvalidationrules">Patching Validation Rules:
        Validation rules may be added to the dataset. In addition, the
        assignment of validation rules to entries can be changed. Use the
        Manage Validation Rules menu to add validation rules to the study and
        use the Edit Entry option to modify the validation rule assignments of
        a particular entry.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>When all the required changes have been made to the dataset, then
    the 'Validate Study' option should be run. This checks that the study is
    in a valid state and is ready to be published (or patched) to the
    database. If the study is not valid (indiciated by red X's next to
    specific checks), then it should be updated to fix any errors reported
    here. If it validates successfully, then the study can be patched to the
    database. Afther study has been successfully validated, the preview option
    should be run to examine the updates to the study in openCDMS Collect. To
    use the preview function, go to File -&gt; Preview and test out the
    changes to the study in preview mode of Collect. If you are not satisfied
    with all your changes, simply exit the preview, make the required changes
    in openCDMS Create and run the Validate Study and Preview options again.
    If you are satisified with the changes to the study and how they appear in
    openCDMS Collect, then you are ready to proceed to patch the study to the
    database. The study can then be patched to the database using the File
    -&gt; Patch option. On successful patching to the database, a success
    message dialog will be displayed and the status bar at the bottom of the
    main window will be updated to show the time and date that the study has
    been patched.</para>

    <para>Because patching a live study impacts several openCDMS modules and
    because changes cannot be undone, users are strongly advised to adhere to
    all the steps in the following patching procedure detailed below.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchinguserscommit">Instruct all users to commit their
        data (including offline data). Do not proceed until this step has been
        completed by all users.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingbackup">The live system must be backed up just
        prior to patching. Contact Support if you have any queries about
        this.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchinglivetest">An exact copy of the live study should
        be published on the test system.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingsaverecords">Create and save a number of records
        and documents in Collect. Ensure that this includes a combination of
        documents that will be changed during patching and documents that will
        not be changed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingpatchontest">Patch the study on the test
        system.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingpatchopencollect">Open Collect on the test system
        and ensure all data previously saved has been handled
        correctly.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingpatchcreatenewdocs">Create new documents in
        Collect (including a combination of documents that have been saved
        previously and some that havent).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingpatchlivestudyonlivesystem1">If all the previous
        steps are successful, then the study is ready to be patched on the
        live system. Patch the study using Create.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingpatchlivestudyonlivesystem2">Test the patch on the
        live system by opening Collect and selecting a few patched documents
        and verifying that they have been handled correctly.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para id="dsdpatchingpatchlivestudyonlivesystem3">Instruct all users to
        login, close any open documents and records. Then they must use the
        Rebuild local caches option. (This is necessary to rebuild caches for
        statuses that might have changed - e.g. rejected docs).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="dsdconcepts">
    <title>Glossary</title>

    <section id="dsdconceptsdataset">
      <title>Study</title>

      <para>A study within openCDMS represents the contents of the
      project/study/trial including the documents and their attributes and the
      properties necessary for the study to integrate with other openCDMS
      products for data entry and user managerment (ie. openCDMS Collect and
      openCDMS Control).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsdocument">
      <title>Document</title>

      <para>An document contains participant data and is part of a record. For
      example, PANSS and Baseline Audit Form are documents. Each document can
      be completed independently of other documents.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptssection">
      <title>Section</title>

      <para>A section is a part of a document. Long documents are divided into
      sections.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsentry">
      <title>Entry</title>

      <para>An entry is a particular field within a document that describes
      how the data should be entered and processed. Entries contain basic
      properties like name and help text for the entry and also more complex
      properties such as dependencies on other entries, validation rules and
      transformers. Specific properties of entries are details further
      below.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsgroup">
      <title>Centre</title>

      <para>A centre represents a high-level geographical region within which
      the study will take place (e.g. North West-Lancashire Care Trust). A
      specification of centres depends on the particular study and its
      geographical reach. A centre contains one or more sites. The centre is
      composed of the hub and the trust codes, and identifies where the
      participant has been recruited.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptssite">
      <title>Site</title>

      <para>Sites are contained within centres and describe a localised
      setting within which data will be entered and maintained (e.g.
      Springfield University Hospital). A specification of sites depends on
      the particular study and its geographical reach.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsdocgroups">
      <title>Study Stages</title>

      <para>A study stage contains all document occurrences for grouping sets
      of document. In a longitudinal study, typical study stages might include
      baseline, 6 months, 12 months.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptstransformers">
      <title>Transformers</title>

      <para>Where potentially identifiable data is entered into the database
      it is transformed such that it cannot be recovered. To preserve
      anonymity, entries may be designed to transform all participant's
      initials, postcodes and NHS numbers.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsunits">
      <title>Units</title>

      <para>A unit is a precisely specified quantity in terms of which the
      magnitude of other quantities of the same kind can be stated (e.g. mg,
      days, weeks).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsvalidationrules">
      <title>Validation Rules</title>

      <para>Validation rules specify particular constraints on the values that
      may be entered for particular entries within a study (e.g. validation
      rules may be set to ensure a date value entered is not set to a future
      date).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsroles">
      <title>Roles</title>

      <para>Roles are specified to define secure access control and
      permissions for users of the openCDMS study.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsstatus">
      <title>Status</title>

      <para>A status describes a particular state that a document occurrence
      may occupy. The status refers to the position of the record in the
      lifecycle of the project. In conjunction with state transitions,
      statuses are used to control the flow of data entry.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsstatetransitions">
      <title>State Transitions</title>

      <para>State transitions are used to control the flow of data entry (e.g.
      it may be desirable to ensure that data entry is completed for all
      documents in baseline before entry of data for the 6 month stage is
      completed). State transitions describe the allowed progressions over the
      lifetime of a record.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsconsentform">
      <title>Consent Form</title>

      <para>A consent form describes a set of questions that must be completed
      before access to data entry for documents may be granted.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdconceptsrepository">
      <title>Database</title>

      <para>The database is the secure central database that is used for
      long-term storage of the participant assessment data.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="dsddel">
    <title>Library</title>

    <para></para>

    <section id="dsddeloverview">
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>The library has been designed to facilitate the reuse of common
      data elements and to provide a community resource for the storing,
      browsing and extraction of these elements.</para>

      <para>This will help researchers standardise studies, by allowing them
      to use predefined documents or create documents containing predefined
      elements during study design. This provides flexibility in designing
      studies while also allowing consistency across studies and improving
      quality through validation of elements (see <link
      linkend="dsddelelementapproval"> element approval</link>).</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsddelelements">
      <title>Elements explained</title>

      <para>The library stores a collection of reuseable elements. An element
      can be an document, a part of an document, such as a question or
      description (collectively known as entries), or a validation rule, which
      is used to restrict the answers to questions.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Document</emphasis>: An document held by
          the library is a reusable electronic clinical research form (or
          questionnaire) and contains other elements (such as entries and
          validation rules).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Entry</emphasis>: An entry is an element
          within an document. For example, a description (narrative), a
          question or collection of questions. The elements can be of
          different types, such as 'text entry', 'numeric entry' or 'date
          entry'. These types are the same types that you can add to an
          document within the openCDMS Create.</para>

          <para>Some entries are known as 'compound elements' as they depend
          on other entries. An example of a compound element is a derived
          entry, which references other entries used to complete the
          calculation specified within that entry's definition. As a result,
          importing a derived entry (or any other compound entry) also imports
          the elements upon which it depends.</para>

          <para>Derived entries can have one or more tests associated with
          them in order to verify that the calculation performed by the entry
          is correct. A derived entry with tests can only be approved when all
          the tests are run successfully.</para>

          <para>An entry can be held by the library on its own or as part of
          an document, in both cases the entry can be reused within another
          document inside or outside of the library.</para>

          <para>The library is populated with generic elements that are likely
          to be reused across multiple forms, such as sex, gender, age,
          ethnicity, etc.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Validation Rule</emphasis>: A validation
          rule is used to restrict the potential answers to entries and so is
          typically associated with one or more entries. A validation rule
          associated with an entry is automatically added to the library when
          the entry is submitted, although it can also be submitted
          independently if required.</para>

          <para>To verify the validation rule works as expected it can have
          one or more tests associated with it. A validation rule with tests
          can only be approved when all the tests are run successfully.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="dsddelsavingstudyelements">
      <title>Saving elements from a study</title>

      <para>An element can be added to the library in two ways.</para>

      <para>1. By using the <link linkend="dsddelview">library view</link> to
      create a new element.</para>

      <para>2. By adding an existing element from a study. It is possible to
      add documents to the library by right-clicking on the document in the
      study tree and selecting 'save to library'. Note: it is only possible to
      add new elements in this way, existing library elements must be edited
      using the <link linkend="dsddelview">library view</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dsddelimportingelements">
      <title>Importing elements into a study</title>

      <para>In order to use or edit an element from the library it first needs
      to be imported into the revelant local study. Elements can only be
      edited by importing them into the <link linkend="dsddelopenview">
      library view</link>.</para>

      <section id="dsddelsearchelements">
        <title>Searching for elements</title>

        <para>There are two ways to launch the search facility within the
        openCDMS Create, from the left hand side tree view, or from the main
        menu when in the library view.</para>

        <para>To search for documents, using the tree view right-click on a
        study or the library view icon and select the option from the menu. To
        search for entries right-click on an document and select the option
        from the menu.</para>

        <para>Alternatively, when the library view is open, from the main menu
        select the relevent search option from the 'Library' menu.</para>

        <para>The 'Search' dialog will then launch. You can search for
        elements in the library by name using the 'search text' field, or by
        leaving the field blank to find all elements of the selected type. As
        shown in <xref linkend="searchdialogimg">
             Figure 
          </xref>, the dialog allows you to select the 'Search Type'. This
        specifies how your search should match the element names in the
        database. Your choices are 'begins with', 'ends with', 'contains', or
        'exactly matches'. For example, if you wanted to see all the elements
        whose name begins with 'A', you would type 'A' as your search text,
        and specify 'begins with' as your 'Search Type'.</para>

        <para>If you know you are after a particular kind of element (e.g.
        date entry), you can restrict your search so that only date elements
        will be returned. You do this by specifying the 'Element Type'. The
        search you have specified is summarised in plain English at the top of
        the dialog in the 'Current Search' field.</para>

        <para>The 'advanced' tab allows you to further restrict the search by
        a particular document, element status (i.e to select only pending or
        approved elements) and/or by current revision. The current revision
        refers to the most recent version of an element as stored by the
        library.</para>

        <para>Once you have specified your search, press the 'Search'
        button.</para>

        <figure id="searchdialogimg">
          <title>Library search dialog</title>

          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo></screeninfo>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_searchdialog.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelsearchbrowse">
        <title>Browsing the results</title>

        <para>The 'Search Results' panel (see <xref linkend="searchdialogimg">
             Figure 
          </xref>) shows you the elements that matched your search criteria.
        The 'Results' field indicates how many matches there were. If there
        were numerous matches, only a limited number will be specified
        initially. You can use the 'More' button to retrieve more of the
        search results.</para>

        <para>The top table shows you the results summary, listing the element
        name, current revision level, and also the element type (e.g.
        document, text entry or date entry, etc). By clicking on one of the
        result rows, it is possible to see even more information about that
        particular element in the 'Revision History' table below it.</para>

        <para>The Revision History table shows the complete history of the
        highlighted element, by displaying the past revisions. It displays who
        modified it, when it was modified and a description of the reason for
        revision.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelsearchpreview">
        <title>Previewing an Element</title>

        <para>The preview feature is to help you decide whether you would like
        to import the element. To preview an element, select the desired
        revision level from within the 'Revision History' table (or if none is
        selected the most recent revision is shown by default) and then press
        the 'View' button at the bottom of the dialog. For an document the
        document itself will be displayed in a new window. For other elements
        a dialog window will display the element's properties, allowing you to
        inspect the element details.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsddelview">
      <title>The Library View</title>

      <para>Manipulation of elements in the library is done inside the library
      view within the openCDMS Create. Elements can only be created or edited
      within the library view.</para>

      <section id="dsddelopenview">
        <title>Opening the Library View</title>

        <para>The library view is opened by selecting 'File' -&gt; 'Open
        Library View'</para>

        <figure id="dsddelopenviewimg">
          <title>Opening the Library View</title>

          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo></screeninfo>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_openlibraryview.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelcreatingelements">
        <title>Creating elements</title>

        <para>To create a new document right click on the Library view icon
        within the left-hand tree and select 'New document'. You will then be
        prompted to enter a name for the document and it will then appear in
        the left-hand tree. The document can then be opened and entries added
        in the normal way. Entries cannot currently be created outside of a
        document.</para>

        <para>In the library view derived entries can have tests to verify
        their correct functioning. Tests can be viewed or added by
        right-clicking on a derived entry, selecting 'Edit' and then choosing
        the 'Test Cases' tab. Click on the 'Add' button to create a new
        test.</para>

        <para>To create a new validation rule select 'Library' -&gt; 'Manage
        Validation Rules' and create a rule in the normal way. In the library
        view validation rules can have tests added to verify the correct
        function of the rule. To create a test simply select a validation rule
        within the 'Manage Validation Rule' dialog and click on the 'Create
        Tests' button.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelsubmittingelements">
        <title>Submitting elements</title>

        <para>Once documents or validation rules have been created within the
        library view they can be submitted to the library. They can be
        submitted at any time and once submitted they will be marked as
        'pending'. Any element marked as pending cannot be added to another
        element (for example a validation rule cannot be attached to an entry)
        and cannot be used within a study until it has been approved.</para>

        <para>To submit an element, either go to the menu and select 'Library'
        -&gt; 'Save documents(or Validation Rules) to Library' or in the
        left-hand tree right click on the Library and select 'Save documents
        to Library'. A submission dialog will then appear (see <xref
            linkend="dsddelsubmitimg">
             here 
          </xref>).</para>

        <para>The submission dialog shows you the elements that are currently
        eligible for submission to the library. All of those that are new (not
        yet entered into the library) are marked with a 'Submission Type' of
        'New Submission' and all edited elements are marked with a 'Submission
        Type' of 'Revision'.</para>

        <para>First, you need to enter some comments that summarise the
        purpose of the element or the edits that have been made. Then select
        the element from the list and press the 'Submit' button. While it is
        possible to submit more than one element at once, it may be best to
        make multiple submissions and submit only elements that the comment
        relates to each time.</para>

        <para>It is worth noting that, if you have added a compound element
        that has subordinate entries, such as a derived entry or an entry with
        a validation rule, that the parent entry and all of its subordinates
        will be submitted to the element library.</para>

        <figure id="dsddelsubmitimg">
          <title>Element Submission Dialog</title>

          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo></screeninfo>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_submit_elements.jpg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddeleditingelements">
        <title>Editing elements</title>

        <para>To make a change to one of the elements in the library, first
        import the element and then change the element using the normal 'edit'
        dialogs.</para>

        <para>You can then submit the revision in the same manner as you would
        submit a new element. A subsequent library search will reveal that the
        element's revision number has been incremented. Note that all previous
        revisions of the element have been preserved.</para>

        <para>Elements can have many revisions and only the latest revision
        can be edited. If you have imported an older revision, or if a
        revision has become out of date, simply delete the element and import
        the latest version. The library search dialog will only show the
        latest revision of an element by default, so this should not normally
        be an issue (see <link linkend="dsddelupdatingelements"> 'Updating
        Elements' </link> for more detailed information).</para>

        <para>You will notice that editing an entry will also mark a parent
        entry and/or document as being edited. Note that this is not the case
        with validation rules, when they are edited any entries using that
        rule will not automatically be updated instead they will continue to
        use the previous revision of the validation rule. To update the entry
        you will need to add the new validation rule once it has been
        approved.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelupdatingelements">
        <title>Updating Elements</title>

        <para>Every time an element is saved to the library a new revision is
        created. Each revision records the state of the element at a
        particular point in time. All revisions to an element are stored. This
        means that elements you have imported locally may become out of date
        as they are edited by other people and new revisions are created. To
        keep you informed of any changes, each time you login or use the
        'Check for Updates' function in the library or study menu, the library
        is checked for any updates to your locally held elements.</para>

        <para>If any updates are found, a dialog window will appear asking if
        you would like to replace your elements with the latest revision from
        the library. Pressing 'Update' will update those elements you select.
        Selecting 'Ignore' will make no changes to the elements, but be aware
        that you will no longer be able to submit changes to those elements to
        the library. If you opt to ignore any changes, you will not be
        prompted about updates for those elements again in future.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelelementapproval">
        <title>Element Approval</title>

        <para>When elements are first submitted to the library, or if they are
        saved back after being edited at any point, they have a status of
        'pending'. This means that they cannot be added to another element,
        for example a pending entry cannot be added to a new document and a
        pending validation rule cannot be added to an entry. Pending elements
        also cannot be added to a study. Elements must be approved by a data
        curator first.</para>

        <para>Approving elements is done in a similar way to the submission of
        elements. documents can be approved by right-clicking on the document
        or the library view icon and selecting the approve menu option.
        Documents can then be selected and approved. Entries cannot be
        approved individually.</para>

        <para>Approval of validation rules can be done by selecting 'Library'
        -&gt; 'View/Approve Validation Rules'. In the dialog window that
        appears, highlight a validation rule and click the 'Test &amp;
        Approve' button. A validation rule can only be approved once all tests
        have been run successfully.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddellibraryviewtree">
        <title>Library View Icons explained</title>

        <para>The icons in the left-hand tree used in the library view look
        slightly different to the icons used when creating studies. This is a
        quick explanation of those icons.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_doc_new.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject> <emphasis role="bold"> New
            elements</emphasis>: The element has been newly created and is
            eligible for inclusion in the library.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_doc_del.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject> <emphasis role="bold"> Library
            element</emphasis>: The element has been imported from the library
            and has no local edits.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGrid Dataset Designer User Guidev3_html_doc_del_edited.jpg" />
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject> <emphasis role="bold"> Edited library
            element</emphasis>: The element has been imported from the library
            and has been edited locally.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="dsdentryconfigdel">
      <title>Library Information Dialog</title>

      <para>The element properties dialog for each element from the library
      has an extra 'Library Info' section. This displays some additional
      information held by the library about the element. Each field in this
      section is explained in detail below.</para>

      <section id="dsddelconfigdelelementid">
        <title>Element Id</title>

        <para>Every element is uniquely identified by an identifier. Each new
        version of an element will have a slightly different
        identifier.</para>

        <para>The identifier reflects the authority the element belongs to,
        the element type and its revision number.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelconfigdeldatemodified">
        <title>Date Modified</title>

        <para>The date the element was last modified within the library. This
        can be the date of creation, the date of approval, or date of the last
        edit submitted to the library.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelconfigdelauthority">
        <title>Authority</title>

        <para>The authority specifies the 'owner' of this resource. The owner
        will be one of a few organisations. For example, the prepopulated
        library comprises elements with the 'org.openCDMS' authority. As
        additional organisations begin to add elements to the library, other
        authority identifiers will be added for use.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelconfigdelperson">
        <title>Person</title>

        <para>This identifies the person who created the element.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelconfigdelstatus">
        <title>Status</title>

        <para>The status of the element within the library. Can be one of
        either 'approved' or 'pending'.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="dsddelconfigdelcomment">
        <title>Comment</title>

        <para>This is added by openCDMS Create to display the local status or
        to indicate whether any local changes have been made to the
        element.</para>

        <para>The different messages that may appear, along with a short
        explanation, are as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">"This element has been
            edited"</emphasis>: The element has been checked out from the
            library and has local changes.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">"This element can be added to the
            library"</emphasis>: The element is not from the library but is
            eligible for submission.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">"You do not have permission to edit
            this element"</emphasis>: The element has been checked out of the
            library but cannot be edited because the current user has
            insufficient security privileges.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">"This element is out of date and
            cannot be edited"</emphasis>: The element has been checked out of
            the library but cannot be edited because it is not the most recent
            version of the element. Only the newest version of an element can
            be edited.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">"This element has been marked as not
            editable"</emphasis>: The element has been checked out of the
            library but cannot be edited. This is normally because the current
            user is has insufficient security privileges to be able to edit
            elements or because the element has been checked out
            already.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>