<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2006-2008, The University of Manchester, UK.

This file is part of PsyGrid.

PsyGrid is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as 
published by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of 
the License, or (at your option) any later version.

PsyGrid is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public 
License along with PsyGrid.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<chapter id="securityman">
  <title>openCDMS Control</title>

  <para>openCDMS Control allows Clinical Project Managers to manage user
  accounts for all openCDMS applcations. Through a series of wizard style
  interfaces, Clinical Project Managers can add, modify and delete user
  accounts. It is also possible to view the current status of users, studies,
  centres and roles and to change a user’s password.</para>

  <section id="securityroles">
    <title>Definition of Roles</title>

    <para>To use openCMDS Control, it is important to understand the roles
    that may be assigned to users. The following roles can be assigned to
    users of the openCDMS system:</para>

    <table>
      <title>Role definitions</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Role</entry>

            <entry>Permissions</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>SystemAdministrator</entry>

            <entry>Complete access to everything</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>ClinicalResearchOfficer</entry>

            <entry>Data entry account</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>ChiefInvestigator</entry>

            <entry>Receives whole study status reports, can read
            data</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>DataAnalyst</entry>

            <entry>Can read but not write data</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>TreatmentAdministrator</entry>

            <entry>Can read data and access randomization results</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>ClinicalResearchManager</entry>

            <entry>Can read and write data; can review and approve documents;
            receives all reports</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>ProjectManager</entry>

            <entry>Can manage studies (eg. Security settings)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>ScientificResearchOfficer</entry>

            <entry>Not used</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>RecruitmentManager</entry>

            <entry>Receives Recruitment Progress Reports</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Principal Investigator</entry>

            <entry>Can read data (usually restricted by centre); receives
            study status reports</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section id="securityview">
    <title>Viewing the current status of studies, users and roles</title>

    <para>When openCDMS Control is launched, you will be presented with a main
    window which contains details of the studies, users, centres and roles
    that you have access to. If you double-click on the displayed studies, the
    users will be displayed. If you double-click on the users, the users’
    roles and centres will be displayed. If you do not see anything in this
    window, then you do not have permission to view the current status of
    studies.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>List of users</title>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGridSMUserGuide_html_4c4b5de4.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="securityadduser">
    <title>Add User</title>

    <para>Clicking the Add User button produces a wizard style interface for
    creating a new user in openCDMS. The initial page of the wizard asks for a
    first name, last name and email address for the user to be entered. A
    first name, last name and email address must be entered to proceed to the
    next page of the wizard and to successfully create a user account. The
    next page of the wizard allows the user to assign studies to the user.
    Studies may be assigned by selecting the study in the left hand column and
    clicking on the right arrow between the two lists. Multiple studies may
    be selected by holding down the SHIFT key while selecting studies.
    Studies may be removed from the list of assigned studies by clicking on
    the left arrow sign between the two lists. When the users’ studies have
    been chosen, click ‘next’ to select the centres. Before selecting which
    centres to assign to the user, you must select a study. The study may be
    selected using the drop-down box at the top of the page. Centres may be
    selected and deselected in the same ways as studies (described above).
    When you are satisfied with the centres, the next page allows roles to be
    chosen for the user. First select a study and then select the roles for
    the user in the study. When you are satisfied with your choice, click
    ‘Next’. A summary of the selections you have made will now be presented.
    If you are satisfied with your selections, click ‘Finish’ and the user
    will be created. If you are not satisfied with your selections, you may go
    back and make a new selection using the ‘Back’ buttons. On successful
    completion, a new user will be created and the default password will be
    assigned to their user account. If you are unsure what the default
    password is, please contact openCDMS Support. At any time, you can click
    ‘Cancel’ to exit the Add User Wizard.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="securitymodifyuser">
    <title>Modify User</title>

    <para>Clicking the Modify User button produces a wizard style interface
    for modifying a user account in openCDMS. The initial page of the wizard
    asks for the first name and last name of the user for which you want to
    edit. If you enter a first name and last name for which a user account
    does not exist, you will not be allowed to proceed further. If multiple
    matches are found for the names you entered, you will be asked to choose
    the correct name from a list. It is possible to enter, either the first
    name and the last name of the user, or to enter the user id. If a user
    account is found for the details that you have entered, you may proceed to
    make selections for the studies, centres and roles that a user is assigned
    to. Study, centre and role assignments are made in the same way as for
    add user (see above). You will then be asked to verify or change the
    user’s email address. Finally, the last page of the wizard will present
    you with a summary of the user account. If you are satisfied with the
    changes, click ‘Finish’ and your changes will be made. If you are not
    satisfied with the assignments, click ‘Back’ to return to the selection
    screens and edit your selections. At any time, you can click ‘Cancel’ to
    exit the Modify User wizard.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="securitydeleteuser">
    <title>Delete User</title>

    <para>Clicking the Delete User button produces a wizard style interface
    for deleting a user account from a openCDMS study. In the initial page of
    the wizard, you must provide a first name and last name for the user you
    wish to delete. If no user account exists for the first name and last name
    which you have entered you will not be permitted to proceed. It is
    possible to enter either the first name and last name of the user or to
    enter the user id. If a user account is found, you may choose which
    studies you wish to delete the user. If multiple matches are found to the
    names you entered, you will be presented with a list from which you must
    choose the user you mean. Studies may be chosen by selecting the study
    names from the list and using the right and left arrow buttons (as in add
    user and modify user).</para>
  </section>

  <section id="securitychangepassword">
    <title>Change Password</title>

    <para>Clicking the Change Password button produces a wizard style
    interface for changing a user’s password within the openCDMS system. As in
    the other wizard’s, you may look for a user in the initial screen by
    typing in either their first and last name or their openCDMS username.
    Clicking next, you will be asked to enter a new password for this user.
    The password must be at least six characters, and an indication of how
    secure the password is will be given (for tips on choosing a secure
    password see <xref linkend="securepassword" />). You must confirm the
    password by retyping it in the ‘Confirm new password’ field. Clicking
    ‘Finish’ will cause the password to be changed. If a problem is
    encountered, you will be notified. NB: A user's password should only be
    changed if they have no outstanding local data in openCDMS. Changing a
    password when a user has local data uncommitted to the database will
    result in data loss.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="securityrightclick">
    <title>Right-Click Menu</title>

    <para>From the main window, it is possible to access contextual menus for
    adding/modifying/deleting users and, centres and roles and for changing a
    user’s password with a right click menu option .</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you right-click on a study, you will have the option to Add
        User. Selecting this will produce the Add User wizard with the user’s
        first name and last name filled in for you.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Right-clicking on a user will produce the option to Modify User
        or Delete User or Change Password. Selecting one of these options will
        produce the appropriate wizard with the users’s first name and last
        name filled in.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Right-clicking on a role will produce the option to Remove the
        role. Selecting this will immediately remove the role in the selected
        study from the user. A notification will appear to inform you that
        this action has been carried out.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Right-clicking on a centre will produce the option to Remove the
        centre. Selecting this will immediately remove the centre in the
        selected study from the user. A notification will appear to inform you
        that this action has been carried out.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="securityfilemenu">
    <title>File Menu</title>

    <para>The file menu is a very basic menu that simply allows the user to
    exit the application.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="securitytoolsmenu">
    <title>Tools Menu</title>

    <para>The tools menu contains options to displaying the current status of
    centres, users and roles. It also possible to produce the wizard
    interfaces here for adding, deleting and modifying user accounts.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="securityhelpmenu">
    <title>Help Menu</title>

    <para>The help menu contains one menu item enabling the user to show the
    About Dialog for the application. The About Dialog contains versioning
    information for openCDMS Control and details about how to contact openCDMS
    Support.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="securitytoolbar">
    <title>Toolbar</title>

    <para>It is possible to drag the toolbar to another location in the main
    window – it may be positioned either north, east or west in the main
    window. It is also possible to dock it outside the main window and use it
    as a standalone toolbar.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Control toolbar</title>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/PsyGridSMUserGuide_html_353295cf.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>